Guide to the Mexico Documents Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Mexico Documents Collection
1570-1913
1821-1869
04/1969-027
University of Houston. Libraries. Special Collections Department
1.00 linear foot
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Mexico Documents Collection is a result of combining several smaller artificial collections into one in order to improve organization and facilitate access. The collection chronicles the history of Mexico from Spanish rule to the Mexican Revolution.
Historical Note:
Special Collections collects and preserves historically significant materials. Its holdings comprise a rare book collection and ten main archival collecting areas. In some instances, Special Collections gathers materials on a single topic to preserve them and make them available. In these cases, Special Collections is seen as the creator of the artificially constructed collection.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Broadsides (notices); Correspondence; Land grants; Manuscripts (document genre); Newspapers
Geographic Name:
Mexico
Topical Term:
Mexican War, 1846-1848
Acquisition Information:
Donation.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Mexico Documents digital collection available at http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/1969_027
Scope and Contents
The Mexico Documents Collection is a result of combining several smaller artificial collections into one in order to improve organization and facilitate access. The collection chronicles the history of Mexico from Spanish rule to the Mexican Revolution. The material has been arranged chronologically into four series: the Colonial Period to Mexican Independence to the Mexican-American War, the Mexican-American War to the Mexican Revolution, and documents with unknown dates. The bulk of the collection is from the period from Mexican Independence to the end of the Mexican-American War (1825-1849).
The documents primarily consist of personal and official correspondence, government orders, decrees, and announcements of Mexican officials. Notable individuals include Santa Anna de Lopez, Jose Joaquin de Hererra and Porfirio Diaz. Additionally, some materials document American military actions in Mexico during the Mexican-American War. Lastly, there are an assortment of documents chronicling religion in Mexico as well as business and land transactions.
Many of the documents have English translations available as well as biographical information.
Detailed List of Contents
- Colonial Period of Mexico, 1570-1821
  - Manuscript on vellum, 1570 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Royal Decree Establishing Certain Levies, May 12, 1643 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Petition for land by Captain Diego Gonzalez, 1678-1679 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Petition from the Barefoot Monks to Philip V of Spain, 18th century (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Purchase of property, 1722 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pancho Fernandez letter to Andres de Allende, October 8, 1745 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Juan Ramirez Orozco, Annual Reports of Missions in Mexico, June 4, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Preceptos para la primera clase de gramatica, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vicente de Herrera, Ruperto Vicente de Luyando, and Miguel Calixto de Azedo Decree regarding Mortgage Clerk, December 14, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Real Contada. de Dmos del Nuevo Rno de Leon, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter from Count of Cumbrehermosa to the Marquis of Cosatiyi, [1790?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Order of Viceroy Count of Revilla Gigedo, August 18, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificates of Deaths, Births, and Marriages, April 24-May 30, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Description of patients entering and leaving unknown hospital, June 1, 1800-June 1, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Count of Valenciana Appeal to the Royal Audience of Judgments, March 24, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Decree Establishing Bishopric and Seminary College at Santa Fe, New Mexico, August 14, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General Joaquin de Arredondo correspondence, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Broadside, Royal Decree issued by Juan Ruiz de Apodaca y Eliza (Viceroy of Mexico), May 6, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters from Joaquín de Arredondo to the Commanding General, April 21-June 30, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Various Announcements in the context of the Mexican War of Independence, December 28, 1814-July 15, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence and Announcements from Joaquín de Arredondo, April 8, 1813-November 28, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Decree of Spanish Government Issued by José Joaquín de Arredondo, Broadside, January 22, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Mexican Independence to the end of Mexican-American War, 1825-1848
  - Announcement from Guadalupe Victoria, November 23, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ramon Arizpe, Ministry of Justice and Ecclesiastical Affairs, to Provincial Vice President of Santo Domingo in Mexico, January 30, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arizpe, Ramon, Order concerning Mexican treasury, February 14, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Announcement from Lucas Fernandez, Governor of the Free State of Tamaulipas, March 6, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Booklet “Documents Relating to the Denial of Passport to Mexico,” by A. J. Garcia del Rio, October 4, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Receipt from Mariano Mexia for windows installed in residential areas, September 19, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Santiago del Valle, Government of Coahuila and Texas, to the Municipal Government of Ciencojas, March 12, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Land Grant Issued by the State of Coahuila and Texas to Samuel C. Bundick, October 29, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Petition for land grant by Adolfo Steen, 1832-1833 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gumiano Rao[?], Ministry of Justice and Ecclesiastical Affairs, to Unknown, November 2, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna letter to Governor Don Lino Ramires, December 14, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Account of the Administrative Branches Issued by the Governor of the Free State of Coahuila and Texas, January 2, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Atalaya (Official newspaper of the Mexican government), October 4, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Petition for land and citizenship by Stephen Nicholson, 1834-1835 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Salary Vouncher, March 20, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Announcement from the Governor of the State of Coahuila and Texas, April 16, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Decree Issued by Interim President of Mexico Invalidating Decree of the Legislature of Coahuila and Texas Regarding Sale of Lands, April 25, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Official Newsletter of the State of Coahuila and Texas (nos. 1-5), April 27-May 13, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Relationship of the offices in the General Command of the Department of the Yucatan, November 5, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Military Roster of the Department de Yucatan, December 11, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Broadsides, Supplements to nos. 55 and 57 of Mercurio de Matamoros, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Warning Issued by Commanding General José Maria Bermudez, January 7, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Decree Setting Punishments for Prisoners Taken in the Texas Rebellion, April 14, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Decree Establishing a Military Legion of Honor, April 27, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Interim President of Mexico Proclamation to Mexican Army, May 19, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Announcement of Santa Anna’s Defeat at Harrisbourg, June 4, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Broadside, Condemnation of General Antonio Gaona by Several Soldiers, August 12, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - General Announcement by the General in Chief of the Northern Army to his Troops, November 9, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, receipt for money, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, money for Indian Wars, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Deserters to be sent to Matamoros, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Deserters, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Delivery of horses, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Closing of a road [?], 1836 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Appointment, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Texas Revolution, towns had not filled quota for auxiliary divisions, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Gobierno del Departamento de Tamaulipas, Correspondence, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence from the Bishopric of Monterrey, December 5, 1836-February 15, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - General Vicente Filisola letter to Ayuntto de Reynosa, July 17, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - General Announcement from Manuel M. Escobar to the Inhabitants of Mexico City, October 6, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - General Announcement from Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna to the Inhabitants of Mexico, April 20, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - General Announcement from Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna establishing two forts in Tamaulipas, May 4, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - General Announcement from Valentin Canalizo to the Inhabitants of Mexico, August 14, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - General Announcement from Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna to the Inhabitants of Mexico, October 5, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna correspondence, September 29, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico City, December 7, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Soldiers of the Garrison at Mexico City, December 7, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Arista, General Mariano correspondence, February 3, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, Broadside, March 26, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, Broadside, April 1, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, May 24, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, May 27, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, May 31, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, June 4, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, June 18, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, June 28, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, July 7, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, July 8, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - General Announcement from Luis G. Cuevas to the Inhabitants of Mexico, July 16, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, September 15, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, September 25, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, September 25, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Announcement from Mariano Paredes y Arrillaga to his Troops, Broadside, September 27, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - José María de Tornel y Mendivil, Ministry of War and Marine, to Vicente Filisola, Division General, July 21, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - George Bancroft, Secretary of the Navy, March 23, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Public Declaration of the Interim President of Mexico, Mariano Paredes y Arrillaga, July 26, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Unsigned letter from Vicente Filisola [?] to the President [?], July 27, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Francisco Maria de Olaguibel Decree, October 30, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - General Announcement [?] from Vicente Filisola [?], suggests pattern to be used for establishing Military Statistical Commission of Mexico, [1840s] (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Valentin Gomez Farías Decree, February 4, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Proclamation from Zachary Taylor, Major General of the American Army, March 22, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Proclamation Issued by Major General Winfield Scott, April 11, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Announcement from Thomas Childs, Military Governor, April 26, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Orders Issued by Thomas Childs, Military Governor, April 27, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - General Order No. 127 Issued by H.L. Scott, April 29, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Broadside Decree Issued by Thomas Childs, Military Governor, May 6, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Proclamation Issued by Major General Winfield Scott, May 11, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Order No. 9 Issued by Thomas Childs, Military Governor, May 14, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - General Announcement from Manuel Baranda to the Inhabitants of Mexico, May 20, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Announcement from Commanding General W.J. Worth to the Inhabitants of Puebla, May 28, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Announcement from Commanding General W.J. Worth, May 31, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Announcement from the Ministry of Relations to the State Governments, August 9, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Announcement from the Governor of the State of San Luis Potosí to his Fellow-Citizens, Broadside, August 25, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - D. Firto Siena document, August 1847 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - General Announcement from José Joaquin de Herrera to the Inhabitants of Mexico, September 6, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Announcement from General Bravo, September 14, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - General Order No. 287 Issued by H.L. Scott, September 17, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - H. L. Scott, General Orders to the Headquarters of the Army of Mexico, No. 297, September 24, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Samuel C. Ridgely, Als. Judge Advocate, October 6, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Letter from José María Mendoza to Accountant of Sonora Commissary, October 16, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - William Davenport, Als, Military Governor of Matamoros, November 30, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - General Order No. 372 Issued by H.L. Scott, December 12, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - General Order No. 69 Issued by H.L. Scott, December 24, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - William Davenport, Muster Roll, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Broadsheet Condemning Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, [1847?] (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Peace Treaty between the Republic of Mexico and the United States of America, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Ebenezer Sibley, Als, Assistant Quartermaster, March 12, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Military Citation given by Army General Hipolito de la Vara to Captain Platón Roa for his Distinguished Service, April 6, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - William Davenport, Military Governor letter, April 8, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - William W. Chapman, Assistant Quartermaster, May 23, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Announcement from Manuel de la Peña y Peña to the Inhabitants of Mexico, Broadside, June 1, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - John L. Hamtramck, Colonel, 1st Virginia, Vol. 20, June 20, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Charles L. Burgess, Commissary Agent, June 30, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Special Instructions Issued by the Military Statistical Commission, Ministry of War and Marine, October 14, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 126)
- End of the Mexican-American War to the Mexican Revolution, 1849-1913
  - Joaquín Marróquiz, Ministry of War and Marine, to Vicente Filisola, Division General, February 20, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Mariano Arista, Ministry of War and Marine, to Vicente Filisola, Division General, July 3, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Juan Nepomuceno Almonte, Ministry of War and Marine, to Vicente Filisola, Division General, October 23, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Juan Nepomuceno Almonte, Ministry of War and Marine, to Vicente Filisola, Division General, November 3, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Administrative Order Issued by Administrator of Post Office Department in Mexico, August 2, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Biographical Information about Mariana De Jesus Paredes y Flores, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna’s message to the Mexican people after third return from exile, April 2, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Decree issued by Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, May 7, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Decree issued by Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, December 31, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Letter from María Manuela Moncada y Mendívil to an unknown Spanish writer dedicated to Josefa Moncada, February 9, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Philosophical discourse on suffering by María Manuela Moncada dedicated to Josefa Moncada, March 8, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Philosophical discourse on deeds and actions as evidence of one’s personality by María Manuela Moncada dedicated to Josefa Moncada, May 1, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Poems about justice and peace by Manuel, Ana, and Dolores Moncada dedicated to Guadalupe and Josefa Moncada, April 6, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Marriage Certificate for Marcelino Escovar and María Zenovia Franco, March 18, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Announcement from Dr. Bernardo Gárate and Archbishop Pelagio Antonio de Labastida, September 9, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Letter from Maxmilian I, Emperor of Mexico, October 19, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Street map of unknown city, construction work detail, January to June 1866 (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Love Poem Dedicated to Ms. Concepción Méndez, January 18, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Legal Statement made by Manuel Bueno in the presence of Judge D. Juan MacMullen, March 31, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 145)
  - Letter from Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna to Hamilton Parker, April 22, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 146)
  - Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna correspondence, June 25, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Gonzalo Villareal, receipt for Atilano Sanchez Larago’s payment, March 1, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 148)
  - A. Pradillo to Lauro Carrillo, Governor of the State of Chihuahua, December 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - A. Pradillo to Lauro Carrillo, Governor of the State of Chihuahua, December 31, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - A. Pradillo to Lauro Carrillo, Governor of the State of Chihuahua, January 8, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - A. Pradillo to Lauro Carrillo, Governor of the State of Chihuahua, January 26, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 152)
  - Aquinaldo, E. Account of money due to soldiers, September 1898 (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Porfirio Díaz to Angel M. Cabrera, January 8, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - School Diplomas of the National Primary School in Mexico City, signed by Manuel González, Porfirio Díaz, and Francisco I. Madero, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 155)
  - José María Pino Suarez to Flavio Guillén, November 28, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 156)
- Documents with unknown dates
  - Legal suit involving two brothers for financial difficulties (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Letter Extolling the Holy Inquisition, date unknown, [late 18th or 19th century?] (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Religious Vow [extracted from a book] (Box 1, Folder 159)
  - Announcement from the Roman Catholic Church to those who worshiped St. Mary of Guadalupe (Box 1, Folder 160)
  - Depiction of Fire at Mexico City Cathedral (Box 1, Folder 161)
  - Three A Series One Peso Bills issued by the Provisional Government of Mexico (Box 1, Folder 162)
  - Contract between Jose Mariano Sanchez y Mora and Isidoro Franco (Box 1, Folder 163)
  - Marriage document (Box 1, Folder 164)